If you imagine what it means to be
consistently profitable with your
trading,
in your mind, what does that actually
look like? I'm not talking about like
having a Ferrari, seven girlfriends, and
an STI, or something. No, I mean in
terms of the performance, how do you
imagine profitable trading to actually
be? Cuz I think when most traders
imagine profitable trading, they imagine
this. Like a nice smooth line up to the
right, some small losses along the way,
but nothing too dramatic, no big
drawdowns, no big setbacks, just overall
consistent steady progress upwards.
Nothing too ugly, just profitable.
And to be fair, when I first got started
learning to trade, I didn't just believe
that this was the case. I took it a step
further. I thought, "Well, if that's the
case, then that's what profitable
trading is, what if I just aim to make a
measly 1% every day? I just stop at
that. Not 1.1%, not 1.5, not 10%, or
some ridiculous fantasy. Just 1%." So, I
opened up a spreadsheet, put a formula
in, extrapolated it out, and basically
concluded that I was on track to become
the richest teenager I know. Just 1%.
How hard can that be?
Well, spoiler alert, as you might guess,
very hard. And as you might expect, I
did not end up being the richest
teenager I knew. More like the biggest
[__] idiot teenager I knew. But
although that sounds completely stupid,
it's not too far from how a lot of
traders deep down expect their trading
to be. On face value, you wouldn't
expect it to be that straightforward,
but you still have a completely
unrealistic idea of what profitable
trading is even supposed to look like.
And that false expectation is one of the
reasons that traders end up sabotaging
themselves, and I see it all the [__]
time. Because, depending on the type of
trading you do, profitable trading might
actually end up looking a lot more like
this. So, messy, lumpy, losing streaks,
drawdowns, long periods where it feels
like you're going nowhere, where things
must be going wrong.
And the funny thing is, this ugly P&L
curve that no one would really want, is
actually in most cases the healthier
one, much more than the one that I
showed you before. And listen, just to
be absolutely clear, this has nothing to
do with whether you literally look at
your P&L curve or not. So, don't be
sitting there thinking, "Well, I never
look at mine, so this doesn't apply to
me." I don't look at mine, either,
because I use different brokers for
different asset classes. It's just
inconvenient to have an overall P&L
curve. Haven't seen one in years. But
it's not about the curve itself. That's
just the easiest way to show it
visually. What we're really talking
about here is the expected sequence of
results that your trading approach is
logically likely to produce. And by the
way, if you're serious about trading,
and you want proper training on the
logic and the skill development behind
all of this, I've got a free training
series that's linked down below. But
first, let me show you why all of this
that I'm discussing catches so many
traders out. A lot of traders, and
probably most traders, assume that once
you have an edge, when you're, dare I
say it, consistently profitable, the
results should feel reassuring, as if
good trading should constantly confirm
that everything is working out for you.
Like once you're consistently
profitable, trading results will feel
smoother, they'll feel more stable. But
it doesn't. In fact, one of the most
dangerous points in trading is when you
do actually have something that can make
you money. You've developed the skills,
you can identify when you have an
advantage with a certain opportunity,
but you still expect the experience of
trading to feel like this neat, stable,
emotionally comfortable process. Because
then, every normal losing streak that
you go through feels like evidence that
something is wrong, that you need to
change something. Every drawdown you go
through sends you into a complete
[__] meltdown, and you just end up
wanting to interfere with things,
changing things. And that's when people
start ruining good trading. Because
here's the key idea.
Different trading approaches create
different patterns of results. Now, I
know that sounds obvious, but most
traders don't actually think through the
consequences of that. They understand
entries, stop losses, they understand
risk reward, but they don't stop and ask
themselves,
"What sort of performance pattern should
this approach logically produce?"
Because if your expectations are wrong,
your behavior is going to end up being
wrong, as well.
So, let's take a look at a simple
example. Imagine all of your trades have
a risk reward ratio of 1:4. Okay,
risking one to potentially make four.
And by the way, just to point out to
avoid any confusion, your trades should
not all have the same risk reward ratio.
That's usually a sign of bad trading.
But this is just for the sake of the
example, to make it easier to follow.
So, if that's the case, that you're
trading with 1:4 risk reward ratio, then
if you have no edge at all, no
advantage, you can expect the
probability of a profit to be 20%. That
would give you an expected value on the
trade of zero. Okay? So, in other words,
there's no advantage, no edge, you're
not going to be making money over time.
Each individual trade might be a profit,
it might be a loss, and on average over
time, taking those trades, you end up
with zero. Zero expected value. Now,
traders often think that if you're
taking the trade because you believe you
have an edge, you believe it's a good
trade to take, it somehow means that the
profitable outcome is now more likely
than the loss. But that's usually not
going to be the case if it's asymmetric
risk reward. It would take a [__]
astronomical edge to tip the profitable
outcome to being the more likely one
with a trade like this. So, instead, a
pretty big edge in this sort of
situation would actually be if the
probability of a profit was 25%. Right?
That would actually be huge. So, we can
see from the expectancy calculation that
if that was the case, you'd be making an
average of 0.25R per trade. Okay? So,
again, some trades will be a loss, some
will be a profit, but if you look at all
of them, on average, you're making 0.25R
per trade. And that's very decent
positive expectancy. So, in theory, this
is amazing, because if all of your
trades were like this, you'd be making
very, very good money over the long run.
But what does this actually mean in real
life?
Well, it means, obviously, that most of
your trades will lose. Not some of your
trades, most of your trades. So, what
would your results look like? Would they
be smooth and reassuring all the time?
No, not really. You're going to be
eating [__] most of the time. Loss,
loss, loss, then a jump up in profit,
then more losses, then another jump in
profit. And because probabilities don't
play out in some predictable little
pattern, it doesn't mean that you'll get
one profit every four trades like
clockwork, cuz if that was the case,
that would be really straightforward.
Instead, you might get eight losses in a
row before a profit. Maybe more, maybe
less sometimes. You might get two
profits in a row. But on average, it'll
be about 25% of the time if the
estimated probabilities are accurate.
Now, the point is, if you're taking
trades with asymmetric risk reward
profiles, then a lumpy P&L curve is not
necessarily a sign that something's
wrong. And the more asymmetric your
trades are, on average, the more
different your trading will be to this
chart here.
But it may be exactly what the approach
is supposed to look like. You know,
there's a really simple mental model
that I like to use that helps to put
things into perspective. And it's just
to think about extremes. So, if you
think about things being along a scale,
and you think about what the extreme
would be, either end of that scale, then
you can work from there to find what's
more appropriate for you. And it kind of
helps to put things in perspective. And
so, in this case, thinking about these
sort of lumpy P&L curves, one of my
favorite examples is if you look at the
Black Swan Antifragile style funds, the
ones that profit massively from
unexpected disruptive events. Like in
this case, we can see Universal
Investments made a return of over 4,000%
in March 2020, when COVID was basically
starting to destroy everything,
including the markets. And before that,
Black Swan funds reported annual losses
for the past five years.
But it's expected. You know, they're set
up to benefit from catastrophic events,
and usually that means that they'll make
losses in between, paying premiums,
things like that. But it's expected, so
they don't have a reason to panic. They
know that things are going to be losing
or flat most of the time, and then
they're going to have these big spikes
up. That's how they're set up. But it's
this misunderstanding that causes
traders to screw themselves over.
Because they say that they want
asymmetrical trades. They want big
runaway profits. They say they
understand probabilities. But then, when
they have to face the reality of that,
things change. Four losses in a row,
five losses in a row, drawdown eating
into the last profitable trade, they
stop managing their trades based on the
opportunities, and start managing them
based on their level of discomfort. And
that's the shift. And it doesn't happen
because of logic, it happens because of
discomfort. So, you start moving your
stop loss at inappropriate times,
scaling out too much, closing trades too
early because you want some relief or to
claw back some profit, not because the
opportunity actually calls for it, not
because it aligns with your trading
approach. You basically start trying to
defend your running profits instead of
making the best decisions for the trade.
And once you're in a drawdown, you often
even take bigger risks because of the
break-even effect, which is a cognitive
bias where you're willing to risk more
if there's a chance you can get back to
break-even. And often that just makes
the drawdown worse, so you negative
spiral even more. And over time, without
realizing it, you reshape your entire
trading approach into something that
gives you a lot more emotional comfort,
but most likely reverses any edge that
you actually had. And that's why so many
traders end up with loads of tiny little
profits, loads of tiny little losses,
and no real progress. You know, 1 or 2%
return a month, they're profitable, but
nothing that's like a a big, huge
performance. They basically train
themselves out of the very trading
approach, the very return profile that
would have made them a lot of money. And
like I said before, I've seen this time
and time again with many traders. I'm
certain that most people watching this
have gone through this and probably are
going through it right now.
And this is exactly why I made the free
training series that I mentioned before.
It's linked down below. Because most
traders don't need random tips or some
magical super strategy that supposedly
makes these huge returns. They need to
actually understand the logic behind
profitable trading, the skills you need,
how they're developed, and why you keep
making the same mistakes over and over
again, and why it's holding back your
trading. Now, there's one more
distinction here that really matters.
Not all ugly P&L curves are good. I'm
not saying let's all just embrace ugly
P&L curves and aim for that. Because do
you know who else has a lumpy ugly P&L
curve?
Gamblers.
So, let's not be idiots about this.
There's a difference between intentional
lumpiness and unintentional chaotic
stupidity.
Intentional lumpiness is when the result
pattern makes sense with the approach.
It's expected, and you already know the
approach works, you've got evidence of
it, you've collected data. Whereas
chaotic stupidity is when you're over
trading, forcing entries, moving stops
around only, taking [__] trades, risking
too much, and then just pretending that
the mess is all just part of the
process.
But it isn't. The problem is though, a
lot of traders can't tell the difference
between these. So, even if you're doing
something legit that should actually
work for you, when your performance
doesn't look all like sunshine and
rainbows, you think it must be a sign
that your trading is chaotic and that
you're doing something wrong. And
actually all of this reminds me of when
we were setting up an investment fund
back in 2012. So, we were speaking to
wealthy people from my business
partner's network and discussing the
opportunity for them to invest with us.
And the offering that we were showing
them was something that was quite
conservative, quite balanced, but above
market returns, right? But at the same
time, we were trading our own capital
using a much more aggressive approach
because it suited the market conditions
at the time. We had the European
sovereign debt crisis, we had at any
month the Federal Reserve were going to
announce the next round of quantitative
easing. And I talk about this time a
lot, like our members get sick of me
talking about it probably by now because
the thing is in that period of time, the
trading conditions were unlike anything
I've ever seen before then or since
then. Like yes, we've had volatility
since then, we had volatility before
then, so that's nothing unusual.
But at that particular time, the big
market moves were so easy to anticipate.
It was a case of when, not if. Things
were so mispriced, it was unbelievable.
So, therefore in that moment, the best
approach was to be positioned for the
bigger move. So, take some short-term
heat, take short-term losses while
you're waiting for the big move to
happen, but in order to not miss that
move, you're best to be positioned for
it, and then just scaling hard once that
move starts happening with conviction.
But that obviously meant a lot of
smaller short-term losses. So, a lumpy
P&L curve was going to be expected. So,
with all of this in mind, when we were
talking to potential investors, there
was one of them that my business partner
knew very, very well. And so we were
talking about what we were doing with
our own capital as well. And they said,
"I want to invest in the jumpy line." In
other words, they wanted to invest in
the approach we were using with our own
capital and not the conservative
approach that we were offering.
But here's the problem.
It's easy to look at the end destination
of the returns and think that you like
the idea of that, cuz who wouldn't like
more profit if you know that's where it
ends up. When you see the end
destination, it's easy to accept the
drawdowns along the way and say, "Yeah,
I could have gone through all of those
because I can see it ends up up here."
But that's very, very different to going
through those drawdowns in real time
without knowing for sure where the
returns will end up being. I mean, of
course we understood that the drawdowns
were temporary and that things would end
up better overall as a result of that,
but someone just investing their capital
and not fully understanding the trading
approach wouldn't necessarily understand
that. So, that meant that when there
were drawdowns, they wanted us to manage
our way out of it. When a trade was
running in a good profit, but it was
still a lot more for it to go, then they
wanted us to bank it. They didn't want
the same approach that was leading to
those great returns that they saw
before, they wanted an approach that
gave them that sort of money, but
catered to their level of discomfort.
And that's actually one of the reasons
why I stopped managing money on behalf
of other people, that and the [__]
nightmare I went through with banks
because of taking on client money, which
is something we'll discuss another time
and not a nightmare I want to experience
again. But actually this year will be
the first time in over 10 years that I
will be managing money for other people
again, so that's exciting. But let's
bring this back to what's relevant for
you and your trading. Because what I've
just described is exactly what traders
do with their own trading. There's a
misalignment of expectations between the
trading approach and the potential that
it can achieve, and what that experience
is actually like to go through. So,
people want the sexy return profile,
they want the aggressive upside, they
want the big profits, but when they
actually have to sit through the normal
mess that comes with that kind of
approach,
they [__] themselves and start
interfering. They end up trading some
sort of weird hybrid approach that's the
worst of both worlds, and never give
themselves the actual chance to have the
great performance. So, a lot of the
time, the real issue isn't their trading
approach, it's not their trading
methods, although to be fair, for most
people that is the biggest issue, let's
be honest.
But anyway, the problem is that their
expectations don't match the reality of
executing it. And this is why so many
traders end up confused. Because like I
said before, you think profitable
trading should reassure you, but
depending on your trading approach,
profitable trading might feel like
repeated disappointment interrupted by
occasional moments where the edge
finally pays you.
And if you need frequent emotional
rewards in order to stay consistent,
you'll keep interfering with any trading
approach that doesn't give you that.
Which means that some people are just
trading the wrong approach. They're
trying to force themselves into a return
profile that doesn't suit them
psychologically.
And that matters. Because if your
trading approach only works when you can
tolerate this,
but you keep trying to turn it into
this,
you're just going to ruin it. So, with
all of this in mind, here are some
questions that I really want you to
think about. Like just go for a walk and
think them through, write them down on
the notes app on your phone or
something.
Okay, so the first question.
What sort of result pattern should your
current trading approach logically
produce? Not what you wish it looked
like, not what you hope it looks like.
What is actually logical for your
trading approach?
Second,
is your trading currently producing that
kind of pattern?
Or are you maybe distorting it with your
behavior? Because a lot of traders don't
know whether the approach is actually
the problem or whether it's just them
murdering their trades. So, I want you
to think about it. Maybe you can go and
get your trade data, look in your
trading journal, figure it out, right?
Spend some time thinking about it. And
third,
that looks like ET's hand. When you
manage your trades,
are you actually following the logic of
the opportunity or are you just trying
to reduce your level of discomfort? Like
this one is very difficult for you to be
honest with yourself about because
you'll get influenced by what you end up
doing. So, here's what I want you to do.
Go in your trading journal and find
trades that you took a little while ago.
So, don't review your trades like
straight after they're closed, but go
and look at ones from last month or
something like that.
And look at where you entered the trade,
pull it up on your chart either replay
mode in TradingView or a trading
simulator,
do all the analysis, take the entry, and
then think through the logic of the
opportunity and how you would manage it,
right? Try to be completely in line with
what's logical for your trading
approach, what's logical for the context
of the market.
Come to the end of that trade and
compare it to what you actually did.
There you go. There's a straightforward
way to compare it. I know it's difficult
to do that, but if you can be honest
with yourself about why you closed the
trade, like with our members a lot of
time they'll tell me, "Oh, it's because
I panicked or there was like I was
scared about losing the profit." or
things like that. If you can get to that
level of honesty, it's going to be so
much better for you. Okay, so when you
look at your answers to those questions,
and again, I really hope that you're
going to go through them deeply and not
just give like a one-sentence answer
that comes from the top of your head,
otherwise it's pointless. When you go
through your answers, I want you to
think about two things.
Firstly, how you can start getting out
of your own way and let things play out
correctly. And you know, one of the
reasons that people don't actually allow
things to play out correctly is because
they don't really believe deep down that
their trading approach is going to lead
them to being profitable. So, if they've
got a profit, even if it's a small one,
they grab it because they're so afraid
of losing it, they'll take what they
can.
Now, we have a great video on measuring
your trading edge so that you can
actually test whether your approach is
going to make you money or not, and then
you'll have the evidence that you can
rely upon. So, you can watch it,
wherever it's linked up here, I think it
is.
Okay, so that's the first thing I want
you to think about. And secondly, I want
you to think about this.
Do you think that this is the right
trading approach for you? You have to be
honest with yourself again, that's a
recurring theme here. And even though
you might like the idea of that trading
approach, you might like the idea of
what it can do for your performance, if
you know that you can't realistically
execute it in the way that it should be
executed,
it might be time to make some changes,
but deliberate changes being made
logically so that you don't end up with
this sort of typical hybrid approach
that leads you nowhere like I explained
before where you're taking small
profits, small losses, and really sort
of breaking even or marginally
profitable, but actually making
deliberate choices that place your
strengths, that avoid your weaknesses,
and leads to good performance.
So, the point of this video is simple.
Most people have the wrong idea of what
profitable trading actually looks like.
A profitable P&L curve does not have to
look smooth. And if you expect it to,
like what everyone on social media is
showing you, there's a good chance you
end up self-sabotaging.
So, don't judge your trading by whether
the results feel right or not. Judge it
based on real, undeniable data and
whether your performance is
mathematically logical for what you're
doing. And as I mentioned before, if
you're realizing that you've been
judging your trading completely wrong,
that you maybe don't have the founda-
-tions that you need, you haven't
developed the skills, maybe you don't
even know what a trading approach should
actually look like, I've put together a
free training series that goes much,
much deeper into the real logic and the
real skill development behind profitable
trading. Not [__] magical
strategies, not [__] magical
shortcuts. Real training for traders who
want to take this seriously. So, if that
sounds like you, something you're
interested in, go to the link in the
description or the pinned comment. It's
free to sign up. You can get started
straight away. Thanks for watching.